Palestine Statehood Committee "Concerning the campaigns for a Jewish Army; to save the Jewish people of Europe and the establishment of a Hebrew Republic in Palestine" Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
The Answer; Jews; World War, 1939-1945; Zionism; Israel; Middle East; Palestine; Begin, Menachem, 1913-1992; Ben-Eliezer, Arieh, -1970; Bercovici, Konrad, 1882-1961; Bromfield, Louis, 1896-1956; Germain, Louis, 1878-1942; Gillette, Guy M. (Guy Mark), 1879-1973; Gunther, Frances; Hadani-Rafaeli, Alexander; Harrison, Earl G.; Hecht, Ben, 1894-1964; Jabotinsky, Eri, 1910-1969; Jabotinsky, Vladimir, 1880-1940; Johnson, Edwin Clifford, 1882-; Kook, Hillel, 1915-2001; Lerner, Max, 1902-1992; Lourié, Arthur, 1892-1966; Merlin, Samuel; Pell, Herbert Claiborne, 1884-1961; Rifkin, Maurice; Rogers, Will, 1911-1993; Selden, Harris Louis; Smertenko, Johan J. (Johan Jacob), -1983; Somers, Andrew L. (Andrew Lawrence), 1895-1949; Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972; Undset, Sigrid, 1882-1949; Van Paassen, Pierre, 1895-1968; Wechsler, Gabriel A.; Wise, Stephen S. (Stephen Samuel), 1874-1949; Ziff, William B. (William Bernard), 1898-1953; American Friends of a Jewish Palestine; American League for a Free Palestine; Committee for an Army of Stateless and Palestinian Jews; Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe; Hebrew Committee of National Liberation; Irgun tsevaʼi leʼumi
- Correspondence, 1937-1959; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains correspondence of the American Friends of a Jewish Palestine, the Committee for a Jewish Army, the Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, the American League for a Free Palestine, and the Hebrew Committee of National Liberation. Since most of the individuals whose correspondence appears in Series I served on more than one committee and the work of the committees was closely interrelated, no attempt was made to keep the correspondence of each indiviual or organization separate. The arrangement of the Series is chronological.
  In addition to original letter, Series I contains typed copies of correspondence. Because of the rapid deterioration of the paper used, electrostatic copies ahve been made for preservation and filed in Series I in place of the typed copies.
  Following the chronologically arranged correspondence in Series I are seven folders containing electrostatic copies of corresopndence and memoranda from the Franklin Delano Roosevelt Library and the Library of Congress concerning the United States policy in the Middle East, the War Refugee Board, and the War Crimes Commission. Series I also contains typed cross references which refer to material located in the original microfilm (reels #1-12).
  Conditions Governing Access
  This material is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 53 instead of the originals.
  - General
    - 1937-1946 April (Box 1, Folder 1-26, Reel U1)
    - 1946 May-1948 September (Box 2, Folder 27-52, Reel U2)
    - 1948 October-1949 June (Box 3, Folder 53-58, Reel U3)
    - 1949 July-December, 1950 April 11, 1951 February 25, 1953 June 29, 1959 December 13 (Box 3, Folder 59, Reel U3)
    - Undated (Box 3, Folder 60, Reel U3)
  - Correspondence and memoranda reproduced from the Franklin Delano Roosevelt Library
    - Franklin D. Roosevelt, 1940-1945 April (Box 3, Folder 61-63, Reel U3)
    - War Refugee Board, 1944 January-1945 (Box 3, Folder 64-66, Reel U3)
  - United States State Department, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 67, Reel U3)
    Consists of correspondence and memoranda reproduced from the Library of Congress
- Public statements, press releases, reports, and clippings, 1938-1950; Series II
  Series II consists of press releases, reports, memoranda, minutes of meetings, newsletters, pamphlets, public addresses, magazine articles, and news clippings, arranged chronologically. Undated brochures, leaflets, and posters have been placed at the end of the series, along with some copies of legal papers and a folder of financial records.
  - 1938-1943 June (Box 4, Folder 1-4, Reel U3)
  - 1938-1943 June (Box 4, Folder 5-9, Reel U4)
  - Clippings: Emergency coference to save the Jewish people of Europe, and "We Shall Never Die" pageant, 1943 July (Box 4, Folder 10, Reel U4)
  - Newsletter: Committee for a Jewish Army, 1943 July (Box 4, Folder 11, Reel U4)
  - Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, 1943 July 20-25
    - Programs (Box 4, Folder 12, Reel U4)
    - Papers prepared for the conference: "From Evian to Bermuda," and "Realistic Possibilities to Rescue the Jews from the Satellite Countries of Europe" (Box 4, Folder 12, Reel U4)
    - Papers prepared for the conference: "The White Paper Policy in Palestine and the Problem of Saving the Jewish People of Europe," and "Memorandum on the Findings of the Emergency Conference to Save the Jewish People of Europe" (Box 4, Folder 13, Reel U4)
  - 1943 August-1944 February (Box 4, Folder 14-15, Reel U4)
  - 1944 March-1944 July 31 (Box 5, Folder 16-21, Reel U5)
  - Emergency Conference to Save the Jewish People of Europe, 1944 August 7-8 (Box 5, Folder 22, Reel U5)
    "A Year in the Service of Humanity. A Survey of the Activities of the Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, July 1943 - August 1944" "Communications with the Red Cross in Connection with the Hungarian Situation"
  - 1944 August 1-1944 October (Box 5, Folder 23-25, Reel U5)
  - 1944 November-1945 December (Box 6, Folder 26-34, Reel U5)
  - Correspondence in re: the Ben Hecht, 1946-1947
    General note
    See: Repatriation, Series III.
  - 1946 January-1946 June 15 (Box 6, Folder 35-39, Reel U6)
  - 1946 June 16-1946 December (Box 7, Folder 40-47, Reel U6)
  - Palestine Trip, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 48, Reel U6)
  - 1947 January (Box 7, Folder 49, Reel U6)
  - National Convention of the American League for a Free Palestine, 1947 February 8-9 (Box 7, Folder 50, Reel U6)
  - National Convention of the American League for a Free Palestine, 1947 February 8-9 (Box 8, Folder 51, Reel U6)
  - 1947 February-1947 December (Box 8, Folder 52-53, Reel U6)
  - 1947 February-1947 December (Box 8, Folder 54-56, Reel U7)
  - Correspondence in re: the Altalena, 1948
  - 1948 January-1948 April (Box 8, Folder 57-59, Reel U7)
  - Emergency Conference to Propose a United States Policy for Palestine and the Middle East, 1948 May 8-9 (Box 8, Folder 60, Reel U7)
  - Emergency Conference to Propose a United States Policy for Palestine and the Middle East: scrapbook
    See: Microfilm reel 15 (or box 27).
  - 1948 May-July (Box 8, Folder 61-62, Reel U7)
  - 1948 August-1949 December (Box 9, Folder 63-66, Reel U7)
  - Undated (Box 9, Folder 67, Reel U7)
  - American Friends of a Jewish Palestine: certificate of incorporation, constitution, and by-laws, 1939 September 6 (Box 9, Folder 68, Reel U7)
  - American Friends of a Jewish Palestine, Committee for a Jewish Army, Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe: pamphlets, bulletins, brochures, Undated (Box 9, Folder 69, Reel U7)
  - American League for a Free Palestine
    - Certificate of incorporation (2 copies), exemption affidavit, 1943 December 29 (Box 9, Folder 70, Reel U7)
    - Certificate of registration in Pennsylvania as a non-profit organization, 1945 October 22 (Box 9, Folder 70, Reel U7)
    - Pamphlets, brochures, posters, 1945-1947, undated (Box 9, Folder 71, Reel U8)
  - British League for a Free Palestine: Posters, brochures, memo, Undated (Box 9, Folder 72, Reel U8)
  - Financial papers: American League for a Free Palestine and Hebrew Committee of National Liberation, 1946-1948, undated (Box 9, Folder 73, Reel U8)
  - Problems of World War II and its aftermath, Part 2, Committee on International Relations, volume II, 1943-1950 (Box 9a, Reel U8)
- Subject files, 1933-1972; Series III
  Series III consists of correspondence, memoranda, reports, interviews, and printed matter, arranged by subject. There are files on specific individuals and special topics; these are arranged alphabetically. Note: While the correspondence in Series I contains few letters after 1949, much of the correspondence appearing in Series III dates from 1950-1972.
  - Begin, Menachem, clippings, 1951-1972 (Box 10, Folder 1, Reel U8)
  - Ben Eliezer, Arieh
    - "The Case of Arieh Ben Eliezer," account of his arrest and detention by the British, prepared by the American League for a Free Palestine, Circa 1946 (Box 10, Folder 2, Reel U8)
    - Correspondence and memoranda in re: efforts to secure his release, 1943-1945 (Box 10, Folder 3, Reel U8)
    - Correspondence and memoranda in re: efforts to secure his release, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 4, Reel U8)
    - Copies of his letters from prison, 1945-1948 (Box 10, Folder 5, Reel U8)
    - Clippings, 1951-1970 (Box 10, Folder 6, Reel U8)
    - Report on Arieh Ben Eliezer's activities in the United States by Alexander Wilf (Box 10, Folder 7, Reel U8)
    - Copy of TLS, S. Merlin to Judith Ben Eliezer on death of her husband, and her reply, 1971 June 7, 17 (Box 10, Folder 7, Reel U8)
  - Berchin, Michael, 1940, undated (Box 10, Folder 8, Reel U8)
    Consists of correspondence and a biographical sketch.
  - Bergson, Peter H. (Hilel Kook), correspondence, 1944-1946, 1951-1972 (Box 10, Folder 9, Reel U8)
  - Bergson, Peter H. (Hilel Kook), articles and clippings, 1944-1964, undated (Box 10, Folder 10, Reel U8)
  - Gillette, Guy M., correspondence, biographical notes, 1962, undated (Box 10, Folder 11, Reel U8)
  - Gunther, Frances, correspondence re: death of Frances Gunther, eulogies, program from memorial meeting, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 12, Reel U8)
  - Hecht, Ben
    - Correspondence of Ben and Rose Hecht with Samuel Merlin, Peter Bergson, and others, 1948, 1958-1964, undated (Box 10, Folder 13, Reel U8)
    - "A Champion in Chains", Undated (Box 10, Folder 14, Reel U8)
    - "A Jewish Fairy Tale", Undated (Box 10, Folder 14, Reel U8)
    - "Song of a Palestinian", Undated (Box 10, Folder 14, Reel U8)
    - "We Will Never Die": text of the pageant, programs, and invitation, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 15, Reel U8)
    - "A Flag is Born": text, playbills, program, and invitations, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 16, Reel U8)
    - "A Flag is Born": reviews, notes, and sketches, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 17, Reel U8)
    - Clippings, advertisements, and reviews, 1961-1969 (Box 10, Folder 18, Reel U8)
  - Helpern, Jeremiah, correspondence and clippings, 1953, 1956, 1963, undated (Box 10, Folder 19, Reel U8)
  - Jabotinsky, Eri, correspondence and clippings, 1951-1969, undated (Box 10, Folder 20, Reel U8)
  - Jabotinsky, Vladimir Evgen'evich
    - Clippings, 1935-1972, undated (Box 10, Folder 21, Reel U8)
    - Correspondence and memorabilia of Samuel Merlin re: ceremonies on the return of V. Jabotinsky's remains to Israel, 1964, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 22, Reel U9)
    - "Introduction to the Theory of Society and Economics (short draft)," typed copy, Undated (Box 11, Folder 23, Reel U9)
  - Merlin, Samuel
    - "The Present Emergency. Its Dangers and Opportunities. A Report of Consultations in Paris.", Undated (Box 11, Folder 24, Reel U9)
    - "The Irgun-Haganah Negotiations. A Warning Against Rumor-mongering.", Undated (1947?) (Box 11, Folder 24, Reel U9)
    - ALS in Hebrew from David Tidhar to Samuel Merlin, 1961 February 10 (Box 11, Folder 24, Reel U9)
  - Stawsky, Abrasha, clippings, 1933-1966 (Box 11, Folder 25, Reel U9)
  - Van Paassen, Pierre
    - Letter to Kenneth Leslie, editor of The Protestant, on the Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, 1944 April (Box 11, Folder 26, Reel U9)
    - Replies by Samuel Merlin and Johan J. Smertenko, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 26, Reel U9)
    - Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, Inc. v. Van Paassen et al., Undated (Box 11, Folder 27, Reel U9)
    - Speech at Manhattan Center, 1941 June 25 (Box 11, Folder 28, Reel U9)
    - Address at the Inaugural Session of the Committee for a Jewish Army, 1941 December 4 (Box 11, Folder 28, Reel U9)
    - Clippings, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 28, Reel U9)
  - Zaar, Isaac
    - Correspondence, clipping, 1952, 1957, undated (Box 11, Folder 29, Reel U9)
    - Speech, "Fifty years of Zionism", 1945 March 13
      See: Series II, 1945 Mar 13.
  - Zabrovsky, Eliezer
    See: Arieh Ben Eliezer, box 10, folders 2-7.
  - "Dramatis personae," clippings file on selected individuals
    - B-K, Undated (Box 11, Folder 30, Reel U9)
    - L-R, Undated (Box 11, Folder 31, Reel U9)
    - S-Z, Undated (Box 11, Folder 32, Reel U9)
  - Oral History: Hebrew University, Institute of Contemporary Jewry. Division of Oral Documentation. Research on the Revisionist movement. Irgun Tsvai Leumi, and Lohame Herut Yisrael.
    - Peter H. Bergson, interviewed by Nathan Kohen, interviews 1-3, 1968 September 26, October 3, November 2 (Box 11, Folder 33, Reel U9)
    - Peter H. Bergson, interviewed by Nathan Kohen, interviews 4-5, 1968 November 7, 11 (Box 11, Folder 34, Reel U9)
    - Sam Dubiner, interviewed by David Shapira, 1970 June 15 (Box 11, Folder 35, Reel U9)
    - Alexander Hadani-Rafaeli, interviewed by David Shapira, interviews 1-3, 1970 March 5, April 6, 9 (Box 11, Folder 36, Reel U9)
    - Eri Jabotinsky, interviewed by Nathan Kohen on his life, the Revisionist movement, Irgun Tsvai Leumi, and Lohame Herut Yisrael, interviews 1-3, 1968 August 8, 29, September 19 (Box 11, Folder 37, Reel U9)
    - Jacob Meridor, interviewed by Nathan Kohen, 1966 May 10 (Box 11, Folder 38, Reel U9)
    - Jacob Vinchel [Winchell?], interviewed by Nathan Kohen, 1967 January 6 (Box 11, Folder 39, Reel U9)
  - Hebrews and Jews
    - "The Hebrew movement," by Horon, 1947 January (Box 12, Folder 40, Reel U9)
    - "Israel and Zionism," by Eri Jabotinsky, 1952 (Box 12, Folder 40, Reel U9)
    - "Hebrews and Jews," by A. Gurevich, Undated (Box 12, Folder 40, Reel U9)
    - "The Right of Stateless and Palestinian Jews to Nationhood", Undated (Box 12, Folder 40, Reel U9)
    - Clippings, 1962, 1964 (Box 12, Folder 40, Reel U9)
  - Irgun Zvai Leumi
    - Correspondence, memoranda, 1946-1968. undated (Box 12, Folder 41, Reel U9)
    - Public statements, bulletins, pamphlets, 1939-1948 (Box 12, Folder 42, Reel U9)
    - Public statements, bulletins, pamphlets, Undated (Box 12, Folder 43, Reel U9)
    - "Memorandum to the American members of the Inquiry Committee", Undated (Box 12, Folder 44, Reel U9)
    - Memorandum to the United Nations, 1947 April (Box 12, Folder 45, Reel U9)
    - Report of conference between IZL and UNSCOP, 1947 June (Box 12, Folder 45, Reel U9)
    - Irgun Letter to United Nations delegates, 1947 September (Box 12, Folder 45, Reel U9)
    - "Palestine in Revolt," by Johan Smertenko, New Background, number 26, Circa 1947 (Box 12, Folder 46, Reel U9)
    - "Memorandum on Aims and Requirements of Shelach", Circa 1950 February (Box 12, Folder 47, Reel U9)
    - "Petition to Henry Morgenthau, Jr., Chairman, United Jewish Appeal", Undated (Box 12, Folder 47, Reel U9)
    - Dir Yassir incident: copy of Anti-Defamation League memo, and pamphlet of the United Zionists Revisionists of America, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 48, Reel U9)
    - Clippings, 1962-1972 (Box 12, Folder 49, Reel U9)
    - Irgun Zvai Leumi. Political activities in the United States.
      See: Oral history, box 11
  - Repatriation (Aliyah Bet - Extra Quota Immigration to Palestine)
    - Memoranda of the H. C. N. L. and the Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe; copy of Earl G. Harrison's report to President Truman, The Plight of the Displaced Jews in Europe, 1944-1948, undated (Box 12, Folder 50, Reel U10)
    - American League for a Free Palestine: Confidential. A Living Report. Repatriation Committee. (Original copy before printing), Circa 1946 (Box 12, Folder 51, Reel U10)
    - S. S. Ben Hecht (S. S. Abril), correspondence, memoranda, depositions, clippings, 1946-1950 (Box 12, Folder 52, Reel U10)
    - S. S. Ben Hecht (S. S. Abril), Tyre Shipping Company: correspondence, records, and receipts, 1946-1947 (Box 12, Folder 53, Reel U10)
    - S. S. Altalena, correspondence, 1948-1949, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 54, Reel U10)
    - S. S. Altalena, public statements, depositions, memoranda, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 55, Reel U10)
    - S. S. Altalena, clippings, 1948-1971 (Box 13, Folder 56, Reel U10)
    - M. S. Zesta, Seven States Clipping Company: correspondence, survey reports, 1947 (Box 13, Folder 56a, Reel U10)
  - Zionist organizations, in re: conflict with Bergson committees, 1937-1949, 1958-1971, undated (Box 13, Folder 57-59, Reel U10)
    Consists of correspondence, public statements, and clippings.
- The Answer, advertisements, and clippings, 1941-1949; Series IV
  Series IV consists of issues of The Answer publication, files of clippings, lists of advertisements and mailings sponsored by the various committees, and copies of the advertisements themselves. There are twenty-two scrapbooks, six folios, and one archive box of material.
  - The Answer, 1941-1946 September (Box 14, Folder 1-6, Reel U10)
  - Commonwealth, 1946 April-September (Box 14, Folder 7, Reel U10)
  - Advertising Campaign
    - Lists and duplicates of advertisements: Committee for a Jewish Army, 1942-1947 (Box 14, Folder 8, Reel U10)
    - List of advertisements: Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, A. L. F. P., H. C. N. L., 1942-1948 (Box 14, Folder 9, Reel U10)
    - Mail campaign: references to scrapbook entries, 1945-1947 (Box 14, Folder 9, Reel U10)
    - Advertisements: Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, American League for a Free Palestine, 1943 July-1944 August (Box 14, Folder 10, Reel U11)
    - Advertisements: Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, American League for a Free Palestine, 1944 October-1948 March (Box 14, Folder 11, Reel U11)
    - Copy prints of newspaper clippings found in scrapbooks 1 and 2, 1942 February-1943 October (Box 14, Folder 12, Reel U11)
  - Scrapbook 1: Advertisements; Committee for a Jewish Army, 1942 (Box 19, Reel U15)
  - Scrapbook 2: Advertisements; Committee for a Jewish Army; Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, American League for a Free Palestine, 1942-1944 (Box 19, Reel U15)
  - Scrapbook 3: Advertisements; Committee for a Jewish Army, Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, 1943 (Box 20, Reel U14)
  - Scrapbook 4: Advertisements; American League for a Free Palestine, Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, Committee for a Jewish Army, Palestine Resistance Fund, 1943, 1944, 1947 (Box 19, Reel U14)
  - Scrapbook 5: Advertisements; Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, 1944 January-1945 January (Box 21, Reel U14)
  - Scrapbook 6: Advertisements; American League for a Free Palestine, 1944 June-1945 June (Box 21, Reel U14)
  - Scrapbook 7: Advertisements; American League for a Free Palestine, New Zionist Organization of America, 1944 June-1945 December (Box 20, Reel U14)
  - Scrapbook 8: Advertisements; American League for a Free Palestine, 1946 (Box 22, Reel U15)
  - Scrapbook 9: Advertisements; American League for a Free Palestine, Palestine Resistance Fund, 1946, 1947 (Box 22, Reel U14)
  - Scrapbook 10: Clippings file and miscellaneous, 1942 September-October (Box 17, Reel U16)
  - Scrapbook 11: Clippings file, 1943 January (Box 17, Reel U16)
  - Scrapbook 12: Clippings file, 1943 February (Box 17, Reel U16)
  - Scrapbook 13: Clippings file, 1943 March 1-12 (Box 18, Reel U19)
  - Scrapbook 14: Clippings file, 1943 March 13-31 (Box 17, Reel U16)
  - Scrapbook 15: Clippings file, 1943 April (Box 17, Reel U16)
  - Scrapbook 16: Clippings file, 1943 July (Box 18A, Reel U19)
  - Scrapbook 17: Clippings file, 1945 (Box 23, Reel U15)
  - Scrapbook 18: Clippings file, 1946 January-September (Box 23, Reel U15)
  - Scrapbook 19: Clippings file, 1946 September-1947 February (Box 24, Reel U15)
  - Scrapbook 20: Clippings file, 1947 March-September (Box 24, Reel U15)
  - Scrapbook 21: Clippings file, 1947 September-1948 June (Box 25, Reel U14)
  - Scrapbook 22: Clippings file, 1948 November-December (Box 25, Reel U16)
  - Copy Negatives from Scrapbooks
    - Copy negatives from scrapbook 1
      - "200,000 Men Ask the Right to Fight", 1942 February 10; 138 (Box 14a)
      - "Jews Fight for the Right to Fight", 1942 January 5; 139 (Box 14a)
      - "Once Again Too Little...But Not Yet Too Late", 1942 August 18; 140 (Box 14a)
      - "To the Conscience of America", 1942 December 5; 141 (Box 14a)
      - "We Shall No Longer Witness with Pity Alone", 1942 December 7; 142 (Box 14a)
    - Copy negatives from scrapbook 2
      - "Supporters of Army for Stateless Palestinian Jews", 1942 December 7; 143 (Box 14a)
      - "Action-Not Pity...", 1943 February 8; 144 (Box 14a)
      - "For Sale to Humanity 70,000 Jews", 1943 February 16; 145 (Box 14a)
      - "The People Have Spoken", 1943 March 10; 146 (Box 14a)
      - "The Jew Asks for Life", 1943 April 5; 147 (Box 14a)
      - "To the Gentlemen of Bermuda", 1943 April 20; 148 (Box 14a)
      - "To 5,000,000 Jews...", 1943 April 5; 149 (Box 14a)
      - "We Will Never Die", 1943 April 22; 150 (Box 14a)
      - "32 Nations and One Forgotten People", 1943 July 13; 151 (Box 14a)
      - "A Report of Failure and a Call to Action", 1943 October 6; 152 (Box 14a)
      - "My Uncle Abraham Reports...", 1943 November 5; 153 (Box 14a)
      - "How Well Are You Sleeping?", 1943 December 15; 154 (Box 14a)
      - "Time Races Death", 1943 December 17; 155 (Box 14a)
      - "The Only Battle Hitler is Winning", 1944 January 18; 156 (Box 14a)
      - "The First Great Realistic Step...", 1944 January 24; 157 (Box 14a)
      - "The President Has Spoken", 1944 March 27; 158 (Box 14a)
      - "25 Square Miles or 2,000,000 Lives", 1944 May 29; 159 (Box 14a)
      - "One Purpose and One Only", 1944 June 13; 160 (Box 14a)
      - "One Purpose Only-To Save Life", 1944 June 13; 161 (Box 14a)
      - "One Purpose Only-To Save Life", 1944 June 13; 162 (Box 14a)
    - Copy negatives from scrapbook 3
      - "It Can Be Done", 1943 October 21; 163 (Box 14a)
  - The Answer, 1946 October 25-November 15 (Folder 26, Reel U13)
  - The Answer, 1946 November 22-1948 December 17 (Folder 26, Reel U12)
  - La Riposte, 1947 March 28-1948 January 7 (Folder 27, Reel U13)
  - La Riposte, Emergency Conference to Propose a United States Policy for Palestine and the Middle East, 1948 May 8-9 (Folder 27, Reel U13)
  - The Answer, 1944 September 12-1948 August 6 (Folder 28, Reel U17)
  - Printed matter: clippings, newsletters, magazines, leaflets, 1942-1972 (Folder 28, Reel U17)
  - Advertisements; Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, The Answer, American League for a Free Palestine, Palestine Resistance Fund, 1942-1948 (Folder 28, Reel U17)
  - Printed Matter, 1942-1972 (Folder 29, Reel U18)
  - Advertisements; Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe, American League for a Free Palestine, 1942-1947 (Folder 29, Reel U18)
  - Advertisements; Committee for a Jewish Army, Emergency Committee to Save the Jewish People of Europe; Clippings and advertisements, miscellaneous, 1942-1947 (Folder 30, Reel U18)
  - Clippings file; advertisements and clippings, miscellaneous, 1944 May-December (Folder 31, Reel U19)
- Microfilm of records in original order